Inventory of the Aleksei Vladimirovich fon Shvarts papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksei Vladimirovich fon Shvarts papers
1849-1955
81139
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Diary, correspondence, memoirs, writings, notes, and printed matter, relating to Russian military campaigns in the Caucasus and Eastern Europe during World War I, and the Russian Revolution.
Fon-Shvarts, A.V. (Aleksei Vladimirovich) 1874-1953.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
General, Russian Imperial army.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is comprised of a diary, correspondence, memoirs, writings, notes, and printed matter, relating to Russian military campaigns in the Caucasus and Eastern Europe during World War I, and the Russian Revolution.
Russia. Armiia--Officers; Deblin (Poland) Siege, 1914-1915.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--Eastern Front.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.
- "Opisanie boevykh deistvii pod Ivangorodom, s 8-go po 22-e iiulia 1915 goda" [An Account of Battle Action at Ivangorod from the 8th to the 22nd of July 1915], 1915 July 8-22 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- "Zhizn; mysli, dela i vstrechi - vospominaniia Alekseia Vladimirovicha fon Shvartsa, chast' pervaia, ot detstva do Ivangoroda" [Life, Thoughts, Business and Encounters - Reminiscences of Aleksei Vladimiroviek fon Shvarts, Part I, From Childhood to Ivangorod]. Typescript with annotations and corrections, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 2-3)
- "Ot Ivangoroda do revoliutsii, chast' tret'ia" [From Ivangorod to the Revolution, Part Three], undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
- "Revoliustiia" [Revolution], undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Ivangorod, raznye dokumenty [Ivangorod, miscellaneous documents], 1915 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Odessa, raznye dokumenty [Odessa, miscellaneous documents], 1919 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- "Tank izobreten russkim" [The Tank Was Invented by a Russian], clipping, Rossiia (New York), 1941 March 11 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Zashchita Ivangoroda [Defense of Ivangorod], clipping, Mogilevskii Vestnik, 1915 August 2-15 (Box-folder 1: 9)
- "Razvitie operativnoi mysli - Operatsionnyi Plan" [Development of Operative Thought - Operational Plan], undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
- "Nastupaite - no bud'te gotovy k oborone" [Attack - But Be Prepared for Defense], undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
- "Poiasnitel'naia zapiska k proektam ukrepleniia betonom i kamnem pozitsii Rumynskogo fronta "[Explanatory Note to the Concrete and Rock Fortification Designs of the Positions of the Rumanian Front, 1917] (Box-folder 1: 12)
- Odessa- dokumenty i pis'ma [Odessa- documents and letters], 1919 (Box-folder 1: 13)
- "Kak byla atakovana i vziata krepost' Kovno," s planom kreposti i ukazaniem raspolozheniia osadnykh voisk, rabot i artillerii, undated (Box-folder 1: 14)
- "Moi svidaniia s Velikim Kniazem Nikolaem Nikolaevichem,", undated (Box-folder 1: 15)
- "Naznachenie v Trapezund" [Assignment to Trapezund], undated (Box-folder 1: 16)
- "Armas y Defensas,", undated (Box-folder 1: 17)
- Biographical file, undated (Box-folder 1: 18)
- "Bylo delo pod Poltavoi - K 230 - letiiu Poltavskoi bitvy," [It Took Place Near Poltava - For the 230 Year Anniversary Since the Poltava Battle], article, Russkii v Argentine (Buenos Aires) No. 464, 1939 July (Box-folder 1: 19)
- Correspondence, circa 1919 (Box-folder 1: 20)
- "Dardanelly, chast' 1-aia,", 1915 (Box-folder 1: 21)
- "Dardanelly, chast' 2-aia,", 1915 (Box-folder 1: 22)
- "La Defense d'Ivangorod en 1914-1915," extraits des memories de gouverneur de la place, lieutenant-general Schwarz, Versailles, 1921 February 14 (Box-folder 1: 23)
- "Dnevnik m-me Shvarts o prebyvanii v Trapezunde,", undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
- "Dokladnaia zapiska g. nachal'niku Upravleniia Finansov Dobrarmii,", undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
- "La Fortification Moderne,", undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
- "La Invasion de un pais en las condiciones actuales y las obras defensivas contemporaneas,", undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
- "Istoricheskii zhurnal - Voina s vengrami,", 1849 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- "Ital'ianskie aviatsionnye manevry,", 1931 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- "Ivangorod," tom 2-oi, chast' I, undated (Box-folder 2: 7-8)
- "O kreposti Osovets,", undated (Box-folder 2: 9)
- Lettres de Guillaume II à Nicolas II, clippings, 1894-1906 (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Memorandum du conseil unifie du Don, du Kouban et du Terek pour la Conférence a Gênes, undated (Box-folder 2: 11)
- "Mes mémoires sur la guerre et la revolution," table of contents, undated (Box-folder 2: 12)
- "Na Chuzhbine -Tom 6-oi,", undated (Box-folder 2: 13-15)
- "Nauchnye polozheniia fortifikatsii,", undated (Box-folder 2: 16)
- "O noveishikh techeniiakh voennoi mysli" [On the Newest Trends in Military Thought], undated (Box-folder 2: 17)
- "Petit Compte-Rendu de l'Activite de l' ex-Commandant des Troupes Russes dans la Zone Alliee et ex-Gouverneur-General d'Odessa," Lieutenant-General Schwartz, June 1919 (Box-folder 3: 1)
- "O podgotovitel'nykh rabotakh k vosstanovleniiu Russkikh zheleznykh dorog,", undated (Box-folder 3: 2)
- "Prikazanie otdel'noi Kavkazskoi Armii," no. 21, 1917 April 3 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- Kefeli, Iia I., "S generalom A. V. Shvartsem v Trapezunde" [With General A. V. Shvarts in Trapezund], 1916-1917 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Kefeli, Iia. I., "S generalom Shvartsem v Karse, Trapezunde i Odesse, osen' 1915 - vesna 1919" [With General A.V. Shvarts in Kars, Trapezund, and Odessa, Fall 1915 - Spring 1919]. Paris, 1955, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- Kefeli, Iia. I., "S generalom A. V. Shvartsem v Odesse, osen' 1918 - vesna 1919 g.g." [With General A. V. Shvarts in Odessa, Fall 1918-Spring 1919], 1944 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- "Oborona Ivangoroda v 1914-15" [Defense of Ivangorod in 1914-15], 1920 (Box-folder 3: 7)
- "Vospominaniia - nakanune voiny" [Reminiscences - On the Eve of War]", undated (Box-folder 3: 8)
- "Na fronte i v tylu -iz vospomiuanii Antoniny Vasil'evny fon Shvarts" [At the Front and in the Rear - From the Reminiscences of Antonina Vasil'evna fon Shvarts], undated (Box-folder 3: 9)